A Guide to the Papers of Thomas H. Clagett, 1834-1852
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Thomas H. Clagett, 1834-1852
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
5182
This collection consists of ca. 280 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The collection was purchased by the University of Virginia Library from the Symmachus Trading Company of Boston Massachusetts on October 10, 1955.
Scope and Content Information
There are 156 items consisting primarily of letters, 1834-1852, to Dr. Thomas H. Clagett, concerning plantation matters on his Nottingham, Maryland, estate. These include accounts and business transactions involving tobacco, clover and other crops. There are also letters to Clagett about slave trading and comments on presidential elections. Other material of interest include some items involving medical treatments of the era and a series of letters from Phillip Nelson, a free African-American, dealing with financial matters and the problems of relocating his family to Philadelphia.
There are ca. 74 letters and accounts to Clagett from Thomas M. Locke, his Baltimore factor, discussing crops--tobacco and clover--and including financial transactions and accounts. Other letters dealing with tobacco, corn and business transactions are from George T. Hardey, 1847; Baruch Mullikin, 1839-1847; William B. Norris, 1842-1848, Nelson Ryan, overseer at Dr. Clagett's Nottingham plantation; and Sullivan & Locke, 1838-1839. Letters from George T. Hardey, Nottingham, regard the sale of Clagett's crops and livestock. The letters of R. A. Lacey pertain to the settlement of descedants' estates and land speculation. Baruch Mullikin discusses Clagett's crops, his overseer, Nelson Ryan, threshing machines, the plantation's slaves, and the management of the plantation. There are numerous individual letters concerning financial matters.
Slavery is touched upon in various instances, including letters to Dr. Clagett from R. A. Lacey concerning runaway slaves (November 12, 1844) and the sale of Negroes (February 20, 184[7]; from M. W. Jackson about slave purchases (December 20, 1841); from John T. Edwards, payment of wages for slave or hired hand (March 14, 1845); from Baruch Mullikin, paying claims for servants (May 21, 1844) and the sale of seven or eight Negroes (April 14, 1845); and, from Nelson Ryan (Apr. 28, 1943) concerning the purchase of two children of a slave.
There are two letters about the Presidential election of 1844, from R. A. Lacey (November 12, 1844) and from Thomas M. Locke (April 28, 1844).
There is a brief reference to the Mexican War in a letter from R. A. Lacey (July 27, 1847).
Letters, 1839-1841, of Phillip Nelson, a free African-American, pertain to financial matters and the relocation of Nelson's family to Philadelphia. In November 1839, Nelson discusses arrangements for Clagett to send his goods, mentions Henry D. Butler, "a man of color who keeps a public house in Baltimore," and gives accounts of persons owing him money. On December 5, 1839, he writes for his "Old Master" to keep his horse for the winter unless he can get the price for it. On December 31, 1839, he requests interest on money owed by a Mr. Harding, mentions having four boarders, and requests recommendations for "Billy," "Lucy" and "Kitty" so that he may bring them to Washington. He also discusses the living arrangements of "Kitty," writing that she is living with one of the finest families in Philadelphia, waiting on three ladies, "the greatest old Aristocrats in town." A March 3, 1840 letter finds Nelson without money and little prospect of lucrative employment; he is concerned over Mr. Harding's refusal to pay his debt. He also mentions illness among the family and servants "Lucy" and "Judy." On April 7, 1840, Nelson requests that Mr. Devine make him a pair of calfskin Jefferson shoes. On September 21, 1840, he requests the sale of his horse and to enter suit against his creditors and offers his house to Littleton. He also refers to personal news: "Garland" is being an encumbrance to Virginia and he requests a pass for him in order to send him to Philadelphia; "Kitty" has married a Mr. Thomas, a blacksmith that learned the trade near Leesburg; and "Lucy" has gone to Boston for several weeks. During early 1841, Nelson makes arrangements for the sale of his house and the settlement of his accounts. On April 28, 1841, he writes that he is leaving for a visit to Michigan, looking for a possible place to live. In a letter of July 26, 1841, he mentions a proposition by a gentleman who offers to give him some land in exchange for his property; he requests the dimensions of his house and a statement of any improvements.
Some medical treatments of the day were touched upon in letters from Baruch Mullikin - tea made of strawberry leaf (July 21, 1847); blue mass and Dr. Wright's Pills (August 4, 1847), and nourishing diet, tonic and exercise as treatment for stomach disorder (October 20, 1847).
A letter, April 22, 1850, from reformer Dorothea Lynde Dix, New York, to New Jersey Governor Daniel Haines (1801-1877) concerns books purchased for prisons and for Governor Haines.
Contents List
- Letter from P. Blakiston, Carey Lea & Company to Dr. Thomas H. Clagett 1834 Dec 3
- Letter from M. B. Carroll to Thomas H. Clagett 1841 Nov 19
- Letter from A. C. Cazenove & Company to Thomas H. Clagett 1840 Nov 3
- Letter from Thomas H. Clagett to Harry Turner 1847 Nov 8
- Letter from William Cooke & Sons to John Clubb 1852 Sept 10
- Letter from Clement Cox to John Rose 1839 Mar 29
- Letters from F. B. Deane Jr. to Thomas H. Clagett 1839-1940
- Letter from Dorothea Lynde Dix to Daniel Haines 1850 Apr 22
- Letters from John T. Edwards to Thomas H. Clagett 1845-1848
- Letter from Samuel M. Edwards to Thomas H. Clagett 1844 Feb 7
- Letters from James Green to Thomas H. Clagett 1847-1849
- Letter from Alexander S. Hall to Thomas H. Clagett 1849 Jul 2
- Letter from George T. Hardey to Thomas H. Clagett 1847
- Letter from B. F. Higgins to Thomas H. Clagett 1850 Mar 26
- Letters from M. W. Jackson to Thomas H. Clagett 1841-1842
- Letter from R.A. Lacey to Thomas H. Clagett 1836-1847
- Letter from Thomas M. Locke to Thomas H. Clagett 1840-1846
- Letter from Thomas M. Locke to Thomas H. Clagett 1847-1851
- Letter from W. N. & L .H. McVeigh to Thomas H. Clagett 1841 Jan 15
- Letter from Baruch Mullikin to Thomas H. Clagett 1839-1847
- Letter from John Contee Mullikin to Thomas H. Clagett 1848 Sept 14
- Letter from Philip Nelson to Thomas Clagett 1839-1841
- Letter from A. T. Neste to Thomas H. Clagett 1847 Jan 24
- Letter from William B. Norris to Thomas H. Clagett 1842-1849
- Letter from William Nelson Ryan to Thomas H. Clagett 1842-1849
- Letter from Thomas Schinebly to Thomas H. Clagett 1848 Sept 18
- Letter from Sullivan & Locke to Thomas H. Clagett 1838-1839
- Letter from Thomas Swann to Thomas H. Clagett 1846 Dec 21
- Letter from George Thomas to Thomas H. Clagett 1849 Dec 1
- Letter from Robert Winebrener & Company to Thomas H. Clagett 1847 Jul 14
- Letter from Y. Y. Yarman [ ? ] to Thomas H. Clagett 1840 Feb 15